<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jgomezdans</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-07-20T13:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Linearly scaling raster data with GDAL</title><link href="//linearly-scaling-raster-data-with-gdal.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-07-20T13:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>J Gómez-Dans</name></author><id>//linearly-scaling-raster-data-with-gdal.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, it's quite tricky to play around with these geospatial datasets: they
have a myriad formats, these keep changing, and you can never know what
metadata will be available in them. A clever way around this situation
is to use tools that allow you to read most of the data, most of the
associated metadata, and that let you do the usual minor tweaks that
you'll require to get things working. And this means GDAL (for rasters)
and OGR (for vectors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical problem: you get some data you've never seen before, and it is
linearly scaled (so they put it in as a 16bit integer and you need to
apply a linear mapping to get the units right as floating point numbers).
In the GDAL mailing list &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lists.osgeo.org/pipermail/gdal-dev/2012-July/033504.html"&gt;there's a thread on this&lt;/a&gt;
using the MODIS SST product. Obviously, you need a reasonable file format
that is read easily (this mean GeoTIFF), and you need it in the right
units, as you don't want to remember these things. The easiest way to
accomplish this is to use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gdal_translate&lt;/tt&gt;, with its rather handy
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-scale&lt;/span&gt; option&lt;/tt&gt;, which performs a linear scaling. We'll also want to
change the data type to a floating point number, as otherwise results
will be quantised. From the post above, we know what the linear scaling
is, but we need to convert it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bash script that loops over these files could be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;for file in A*L3m_8D_NSST_4 ;
do
  echo &amp;quot;map: $file&amp;quot;
  gdal_translate -of GTiff -ot Float32 \
                      -scale 0 65535 -2. 45. \
                      -a_srs &amp;quot;EPSG:4326&amp;quot; \
                      -a_nodata 65535  \
                      -a_ullr -180 90 180 -90 \
                      -co &amp;quot;COMPRESS=PACKBITS&amp;quot; \
                      &amp;#39;HDF4_SDS:UNKNOWN:&amp;quot;A20030012003008.L3m_8D_NSST_4&amp;quot;:0&amp;#39;\
                      A20030012003008.L3m_8D_NSST_4.tif
done
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="GDAL"></category><category term="remote sensing"></category></entry></feed>